Finding Aid for Department of Atmospheric, Oceanic, and Space Sciences (University of Michigan) publications, 1956-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Atmospheric, Oceanic, and Space Sciences (University of Michigan) publications 1956-2004
University of Michigan. Department of Atmospheric, Oceanic and Space Sciences.
0.2 linear feet
9718 Bimu C146 2
ABSTRACT
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The publications are received periodically from the unit (donor no. 1884 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open without restriction.
Atmospheric, Oceanic, and Space Sciences is a department in the College of Engineering. The roots of space research trace to the founding of two large research laboratories in 1946, the Space Physics Research Laboratory (SPRL) and the High Altitude Laboratory, Meteorological studies within engineering began with the hiring of 1954 with the hiring of Professor Wendell Hewson, by the Civil Engineering Department. Engineering meteorology attracted new faculty and students and began to emphasize areas such as dynamics and instrumentation. The group was moved into Engineering Mechanics in 1961.
In July 1963 the regents approved creation of a Department of Meteorology and Oceanography [Regents proceedings July 1963 p.38] The department's name was changed to Department of Atmospheric and Oceanic Science October 1972 and to Department of Atmospheric, Oceanic, and Space Sciences in 1987.
The Department of Atmospheric Oceanic and Space Sciences Publications (.2 linear foot) are divided into two series: Unit Publications and Sub-Unit Publications. Publications includes brochures and pamphlets documenting the Aeronomy Program, as well as Atmospheric Science, Oceanic Science, and Meterology. Also contains brochures describing the Space Physics Research Laboratory
The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the Department of Atmospheric, Oceanic and Space Sciences. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication. This series includes brochures which describe the individual fields of study of Atmospheric Science, Meteorology, and Oceanic Science. Brochures describing programs, including graduate studies, in the Department of Atmospheric, Oceanic, and Space Sciences are also included. The Aeronomy Program, which involves the study of the upper atmosphere, is also described.
The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs and organizations within the Department of Atmospheric, Oceanic and Space Sciences. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit. The Sub-Unit Publications series includes brochures from the Michigan Solar Energy Measurement Facility. The Space Physics Research Laboratory is documented through an annual report from 1995, undated brochures, and a history written in 1993. The Bentley Historical Library holds one newsletter, entitled the Daily Planet, published in 1989.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Aeronomy Program.; University of Michigan. Space Physics Research Laboratory.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Aeronomy Program.; University of Michigan. Space Physics Research Laboratory.
Genre Terms:
Pamphlets.
- Unit Publications
  - Brochures
    - Aeronomy Program, 1967-1970 (Box 1)
    - Atmospheric Science, 1973-1995 (Box 1)
    - Drift Bottles and Other Surface Current Markers, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Studies in Atmospheric and Space Sciences, 1974-1980 (Box 1)
    - Meteorology, 1956-1972 (Box 1)
    - Oceanic Science, 1969-1993 (Box 1)
  - Flyers, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Disposition of Atmospheric Particulate Matter by Convective Storms: The Role of the Convective Updraft as an Input Mechanism by Donald F. Gatz, 1966 (Box 1)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  - Michigan Solar Energy Measurement Facility
    - Brochures, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Space Physics Research Laboratory
    - Annual Reports, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Brochures, undated (Box 1)
    - Dedication, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Histories, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters
      - Daily Planet, 1989, 2004